Okay, two points I want to hit on. Yes,
the title, but also the longevity effect
discussed by Dr. Ronda Patrick when
discussing a study looking at the
omega-3 index, which is a blood marker
of the amount of omega-3 fat that is
integrated into your cells. So, as more
omega-3 fats are built into the membrane
of your cells, in this case, red blood
cells, the higher your omega-3 index,
which is measured as a percentage. So,
Dr. Patrick had several interesting
things to say on the topic, but she gets
one critical piece of information
incorrect that I'd like to contextualize
as well. Let's listen in first.
>> But anyways, the the thing that's
amazing with the omega3 index is that
people that have the 8%
>> omega-3 index are have a 5year increased
life expectancy compared to people that
have 4%.
>> Five years.
>> Five year. Think about five years of
being around your loved ones, doing
amazing things, enjoying life. Five
years.
>> Five years. And there's studies showing
that they're like you're much less
likely to get Alzheimer's disease if you
have a high omega-3 index. So, the
quality of life is better as well.
>> Yeah. No doubt that's an impressive
statistic. That means that if you have a
high omega-3 index, defined as 8% or
greater, you have a greater chance of
living 5 years longer than someone with
a low omega-3 index, which is defined as
4% or lower. That was mentioned in this
study. I know that because Dr. Patrick
kindly provided references. Honestly,
something that I think that all
science-based communi communicators
should be doing. In that study,
researchers do mention a 4.74
years added at the high omega-3 index.
But therein lies a problem that we'll
get into in just a minute. Let's
continue on for the time being.
>> Um, and I was telling you this
yesterday, and I like talking about
because it blows my mind every time.
>> Yeah.
>> The smoke. So, they they took this
cohort of people and there were smokers
in there. There were smokers and there's
non-smokers. And um and they looked at
their omega-3 index and they found that
the smokers that had a high omega-3
index of 8%. So these are smokers that
are like, "I need the fish oil. I got to
do I'm smoking." You know, these
>> they had the same life expectancy as the
non-smokers with the low omega-3 index.
>> That is insane. You could be somebody
who's running every day but not getting
enough fish oil and then somebody who's,
you know, smoking a pack of marbaros and
taking fish oil and you're going to live
the same amount roughly. This is the
point related to smoking. Hopefully I'm
not too out of line when I say that we
can, I think, all agree that smoking is
not a positive for our health. Dr.
Gundry has entered the chat. Let me know
if you understood that reference. In
fact, smoking is one of the most
detrimental things that we can do to our
body. So, it's pretty wild to hear that
a person can consume enough omega-3s,
but smokes might be in a same ballpark
as someone who doesn't. So you and me
probably but may have a low omega-3
index. However, if we lean on the same
study and we look at the data, we see
that might be the case. On the
horizontal axis, we have the age of the
participants and on the vertical we have
the survival over time. So the higher
the lines are, the better. I'll
highlight the two groups of interest.
The low omega-3 but non-smoking and the
high omega-3 and smoking. Here, see how
the lines overlap? That means that Dr.
Patrick is spoton. They're similar in
survival. Of course, being low in your
omega-3 index and smoking is the worst
of all. However, this is where a big
piece of context isn't being mentioned
and isn't mentioned later on. Initially,
I heard these claims and I was really
impressed. So, I popped open the study
that we've been going over and I was
disappointed because while it seems that
the study is indicating that is true,
the data for the 4.74 years, let's call
it 5 years of added life is based on an
estimate. Meaning these are theoretical,
not based directly from compared data.
The researchers even say that these are
theoretical. That doesn't mean that they
pulled it out of thin air. There's still
data behind it, but they are extending
the data out over time, predicting what
might happen based on a predictive model
as opposed to showing the data that did
show it directly. This is a big deal
because it doesn't guarantee these
results are going to end up being true
when the data is completely collected.
The takeaway here is that we can't make
any definitive claims that a low omega-3
status is actually going to lead to five
fewer years of life, even if it does
seem to track with being equivalent to
smoking, which is a pretty punchy line
in its own right. So then, do we go to
the other extreme that omega-3 is not
beneficial then? No. We have evidence
that omega-3s are still beneficial in
reducing mortality risk. Beyond that,
larger analyses also confirm that to be
true. Still, all of these analyses still
suffer from methodological limitations
that the authors acknowledge. For
example, they fail to adjust or control
for nutrition. And it's even been
brought up that omega-3 could simply be
a marker of generally healthier
lifestyle like eating habits than the
actual causitive factor for reducing
mortality risk. And that's true if we
base things only on these analyses. But
as we've covered many direct studies on
omega-3s on physionic, I'm still quite
confident that is not the case. My
stance remains that omega-3s have direct
causitive positive health effects. I
think the uncertainty is more so based
on these studies the conclusion that we
know how many more years of life
omega-3s will provide. We have
estimates, but we need better data. I'm
going to be going into much more depth
in my full analysis going over different
types of omega-3s and different
mortality risks. If you're interested,
you can find the full video along with
the article to go along with it as a
member of the Physionic Insiders. It's
linked in the description. Not to even
mention all this other stuff that you
get as a member, too. That all said,
that leaves us with a few take-home
points. One, Dr. Patrick brings up a
great point that it does seem that
having a low omega-3 index is associated
with mortality risk similar to smoking,
except how much smoking isn't exactly
clear, unfortunately. Two, I think it's
a bit overzealous to say that there's a
5-year life extension since the estimate
of life extension is just that, an
estimate. We'd need to have actual
better data for that. Although there's
no denying that there are many studies
that indicate health benefits of
omega-3s. And three, none of this should
dissuade someone from measuring their
omega-3 index and aiming to maintain it
around 8% if not a bit higher, i.e. out
of deficiency. You can achieve that
through algae oil, krill oil, fish oil,
or just straight up eating seafoods like
fatty fish a few times per week. But
like I said, there are many studies that
show direct evidence of omega-3s
improving things like our cardiovascular
health. And one that I've covered before
is something that I've never seen anyone
else mention before. I go into it right
here. I'll see you over